<h3>Presentation</h3>
<p>The river Ebro, that so many times has been merely the most picturesque facade of Zaragoza, is today its "main street" and vertebrates city growth in both banks, inviting citizens to walk by them. This is the main legacy of the International Expo "Water and Sustainable Development" held in Zaragoza in the summer of 2008. Related to the theme of the Expo, an Additional Plan was implemented to recover the banks of the river, and line parks along the rivers Ebro, Huerva, G&#225;llego, and the Canal Imperial of Aragon were built.  All these urban and environmental actions form part of the so-called Zaragoza Green Ring (AVZ), a track with more than 10 km long around the city with, benches, picnic areas, areas for children, sports for the elderly, and kiosks with outdoor tables for summer strollers and cyclists. Several works of art were put, mainly on the paths beside the river banks of the Ebro, forming part of the Road to Santiago. Within its 3 kilometres between la Almozara and Vadorrey this path presents  several of the most emblematic examples of public art of the city, some very old and others built for the Art Programme of Expoagua 2008.  </p>
<p><a shape="rect" href="ebro/en/valoracion">Assessment of the Art Programme of Expoagua 2008</a></p>
<h3>Route</h3>
<ol>
	<li><a href="ebro/en/parque" shape="rect">Luis Bu&#241;uel Water Park</a></li>
	<li><a href="ebro/en/tercer" shape="rect">From the Third Millennium Bridge to the Pavilion Bridge</a></li>
	<li><a href="ebro/en/voluntariado" shape="rect">From the Pavilion Bridge to the Volunteers Footbridge</a></li>
	<li><a href="ebro/en/pasarela" shape="rect">From the Volunteers Footbridge to Almozara Bridge</a></li>
	<li><a href="ebro/en/almozara" shape="rect">From la Almozara Bridge to Santiago Bridge</a></li>
	<li><a href="ebro/en/santiago" shape="rect">From Santiago Bridge to the Stone Bridge</a></li>
	<li><a href="ebro/en/lonja" shape="rect">From the square behind the Lonja to the square behind la Seo</a></li>
	<li><a href="ebro/en/hierro" shape="rect">From Iron Bridge to Union Bridge</a></li>
	<li><a href="ebro/en/piedra" shape="rect">Ebro riverbanks at Las Fuentes District</a></li>
</ol>

<iframe frameborder="0" id="arte" width="100%" height="600px" title="Recorrido por el arte público a orillas del Ebro" src="http://idezar.zaragoza.es/clientesIDEZarOL/visorGeoRSS/?georss_url=https://www.zaragoza.es/contenidos/geoitinerariosebro.xml&amp;id=235&amp;escala=25000&amp;maptiptype=1"><a href="http://idezar.zaragoza.es/clientesIDEZarOL/visorGeoRSS/?georss_url=https://www.zaragoza.es/contenidos/geoitinerariosebro.xml&amp;id=235&amp;escala=25000&amp;maptiptype=1">Recorrido por el arte público a orillas del Ebro</a></iframe>
<p role="alert" class="alert alert-info">Author of the Route: Jesús Pedro Lorente</p>

