<h3>Presentation</h3>
<ul id="menu_interior">
	<li><a shape="rect" href="monumentos/en/epilogo">Conclusion</a></li>
</ul>
<p>From the 19th century, it was generalized the trend to erect at the city center, commemorative monuments to perpetuate important people linked to local history, or relevant present or past events. A moral and pedagogical element is added to the evident ornamental goal of urban sculptures, since, thanks to them, different values coming from the heroism and bravery showed in heroic feats and adversities, as well as the virtues of distinguished characters, pass on to the population. This trend, usual in Spain halfway through the 19th century, increased during the rest of the following century and continues right now. In some cases, the concept of homage has changed and also, more clearly, the construction and sculptural solutions used.   From the beginning of the 20th century until now, the center of Zaragoza has been the favourite urban space for these public art events. These monuments narrate many stories not frequently heard of by people who are used to see it. Therefore, it is interesting to stop for a moment and know all the stories that these mute witnesses of Zaragoza past can tell us. From the data related to what is commemorated or represented, we can even know the preferred art styles of every age, the sponsors of this kind of initiatives, and finally the different locations of some of them, that show the need to adapt the growing city to new the demands. </p>
<h3>Route</h3>
<ol>
	<li><a href="monumentos/en/espana" shape="rect">Espa&#241;a Square</a></li>
	<li><a href="monumentos/en/independencia" shape="rect">Independencia Boulevard</a></li
	><li><a href="monumentos/en/aragon" shape="rect">Arag&#243;n Square</a></li>
	<li><a href="monumentos/en/paraiso" shape="rect">Basilio Para&#237;so Square</a></li>
	<li><a href="monumentos/en/sasera" shape="rect">Glorieta de Sasera</a></li>
	<li><a href="monumentos/en/constitucion" shape="rect">Constituci&#243;n Boulevard</a></li>
	<li><a href="monumentos/en/sitios" shape="rect">Los Sitios Square</a></li>
	<li><a href="monumentos/en/costa" shape="rect">From Joaqu&#237;n Costa Street to Felipe Sanclemente Street</a></li>
	<li><a href="monumentos/en/carmen" shape="rect">From Carmen Square to Salamero Square</a></li>
</ol>
<div><iframe frameborder="0" id="arte" width="100%" height="600" title="Mapa Temático sobre itinerarios de Monumentos Conmemorativos" src="http://idezar.zaragoza.es/clientesIDEZarOL/visorGeoRSS/?georss_url=https://www.zaragoza.es/contenidos/geoitinerariosmonu.xml&amp;maptiptype=1&amp;georss_id=2&amp;escala=5000"><a href="http://idezar.zaragoza.es/clientesIDEZarOL/visorGeoRSS/?georss_url=https://www.zaragoza.es/contenidos/geoitinerariosmonu.xml&amp;maptiptype=1&amp;georss_id=2&amp;escala=5000">Mapa de Itinerario por Monumentos Conmemorativos</a></iframe></div>
<p role="alert" class="alert alert-info">Author of the Itinerary: Victoria MARTINEZ AURED</p>