<!DOCTYPE html><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:th="http://www.thymeleaf.org" xmlns:sede="http://www.zaragoza.es" lang="es"><head><meta charset="utf-8" />    <sede:meta title="Arte Publico. Itinerario Plazas del Casco Viejo. Plaza del Pilar" description="Itinerario Plazas del Casco Viejo. Plaza del Pilar" author="" last-modified="Fri Jan 16 00:00:00 GMT+01:00 2009" keywords="Arte Publico, itinerario."/></head><body><sede:content>
<h2>4. Basilio Paraíso Square</h2><ul id="menu_interior" class="nav nav-pills"><li><a href="/sede/portal/arte-publico/itinerarios/">Route Start</a></li><li><a href="aragon">Previous</a></li><li><a href="sasera">Next</a></li></ul>

<div class="dere pull-right margin-l05em"><img alt="" src="/cont/paginas/artepublico/itinerarios/img/4paraiso.jpg"/></div><p>Independencia Boulevard ends at Basilio Para&#237;so Square. At one of its sides we can see the <a href="/sede/servicio/arte-publico/262" shape="rect">facade of the old Faculty of Medicine and Sciences</a>. There are four sit statues of doctors and scientists. These are the only works of the square with a certain commemorative character, since the others are ornamental. Nevertheless, the <a href="/sede/servicio/arte-publico/73" shape="rect">Commemorative Monument to the Spanish-French Exposition of 1908</a> was placed there, serving also as homage to one of it main promoters: Basilio Para&#237;so. Nevertheless, the monument rested unfinished for decades, since Para&#237;so was opposed to its construction until his dead. The bust was put in 1935, after the dead also of his son. As it happens with the majority of public sculptures built for the Exposition, those works of art were made by artists from other Spanish regions: the Catalan Osl&#233; brothers. The demands imposed by city growing, forced the municipality to translate these sculptures, since they hindered road traffic, being moved to a hidden corner of the Parque Grande. We find another monument to <a href="/sede/servicio/arte-publico/258" shape="rect">Basilio Para&#237;so</a> at the entry of the Chamber of Commerce and Industry, a bronze bust on a pedestal made by Florencio de Pedro in 2008.</p><p>The statue of <a href="/sede/servicio/arte-publico/191" shape="rect">Augusto Prima Porta</a>, in memory of the founder of Caesaraugusta, was also put on this central square in the 1980s. After several moves, we can finally visit this work at C&#233;sar Augusto Avenue, at the feet of a small pond opposite the <a href="/sede/servicio/arte-publico/65" shape="rect">Allegory of the Peace Gate</a> and the Roman Walls. </p>
</sede:content></body></html>