<h3>Presentation</h3>
<p>Water is an essential element for the development of life, both in cities and in rural areas. Therefore, the construction of fountains for daily consumption has been a common practice. But, apart from this purely utilitarian function, the fountains have been objects of aesthetic and symbolic ornament in the gardens and parks built along history, empowering the ludic character of water. Fountains to drinks, fountains to do washing, fountains for animals, but also sculpture-fountains, fountains only with water, with or without jets, a wide array that can be found anywhere. </p>
<p>Zaragoza is and was a city surrounded by rivers (Ebro, Huerva, Gallego) and the Canal Imperial. And, the first fountain for supplying water to Zaragoza, dates back from the 18th century, with the arrival of the water from the Canal Imperial to the city. We find another fountain -Neptune Fountain- for the same use, placed at Espa&#241;a Square, in the expansion area built during the 19th century. Nevertheless, during the 20th century, Zaragoza was not a city with many decorative fountains. City growth was subjected to the tyranny of the car and there was not big green areas excepting Miguel Primo de Rivera Park and scarce ornamental elements. The situation changed with the arrival of Democracy and the first plans for the renovation of the old town. New squares for leisure and the consolidation of green areas brought the promotion of art works -hybrids between sculpture an ornamental fountain- creating the coexistence and renovation of the concept of fountain. The fountains continued to be perceived as commemorative monuments, becoming one more material used by artists.  </p>
<h3>Routes</h3>
<ol>
	<li><a shape="rect" href="fuentes/en/huerva">From the Incr&#233;dulos Fountain to the Huerva  </a></li>
	<li><a shape="rect" href="fuentes/en/parque">Miguel Primo de Rivera Park  or Parque Grande </a></li>
	<li><a shape="rect" href="fuentes/en/calderos">Ruise&#241;ores Promenade, Pignatelli Park and the Fountain of the Caldrons</a></li>
	<li><a shape="rect" href="fuentes/en/sasera">From Sagasta Promenade to Glorieta Sasera</a></li>
	<li><a shape="rect" href="fuentes/en/paraiso">From Paraiso Square to Espa&#241;a Square</a></li>
	<li><a shape="rect" href="fuentes/en/pilar">From Espa&#241;a Square to the Pilar Square</a></li>
	<li><a shape="rect" href="fuentes/en/jorge">From the Stone Bridge to Tio Jorge Park</a></li>
</ol>
<div>
	<iframe frameborder="0" id="arte" width="100%" height="600px" title="Mapa Temático sobre itinerarios de Fuentes y láminas de Agua" src="http://idezar.zaragoza.es/clientesIDEZarOL/visorGeoRSS/?georss_url=https://www.zaragoza.es/contenidos/geoitinerariosfuentes.xml&amp;maptiptype=1&amp;georss_id=10&amp;escala=50000">
		<a href="http://idezar.zaragoza.es/clientesIDEZarOL/visorGeoRSS/?georss_url=https://www.zaragoza.es/contenidos/geoitinerariosfuentes.xml&amp;maptiptype=1&amp;georss_id=10&amp;escala=50000">Mapa de Itinerario por Fuentes y láminas de agua</a>
	</iframe>
</div>
<p>Autora del Itinerario: Pilar Biel Ibáñez</p>