<!DOCTYPE html><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:th="http://www.thymeleaf.org" xmlns:sede="http://www.zaragoza.es" lang="es"><head><meta charset="utf-8" />    <sede:meta title="Arte Publico. Itinerario Plazas del Casco Viejo. Plaza del Pilar" description="Itinerario Plazas del Casco Viejo. Plaza del Pilar" author="" last-modified="Wed Dec 09 00:00:00 GMT+01:00 2009" keywords="Arte Publico, itinerario."/></head><body><sede:content>
<h2>7. From the square behind the Lonja to the square behind la Seo</h2><ul id="menu_interior" class="nav nav-pills"><li><a href="/sede/portal/arte-publico/itinerarios/">Route Start</a></li><li><a href="santiago">Previous</a></li><li><a href="hierro">Next</a></li></ul>
<p>Paco Rallo was also the author of the small horse in bronze that, as <a shape="rect" href="/sede/servicio/arte-publico/61">Monument to the Photographer &#193;ngel Cordero Garc&#237;a</a>, was placed at the right bank of the Ebro, at the same time that the lions of the Stone Bridge, just opposite the Lonja.  This street artist usually stood there trying to attract children. In the same small square, we find also the<a shape="rect" href="/sede/servicio/arte-publico/20"> Monument to Lorenzo Pardo</a>, promoter and first director of the Hydrographic Confederation of the Ebro.</p><div class="dere pull-right"><img alt="" src="/cont/paginas/artepublico/itinerarios/img/almozara4.jpg"/></div><p>Opposite to it, on the river bank, it was placed in 2008 the bronze sculpture <em>Wild Relative</em>, that, depending on the position of the onlooker, seems abstract or remembers a face with different expressions, for instance clouds deformed by the wind. This is a typical work of the prestigious English sculptor Tony Cragg, built by Expoagua out of contest as hommage to the cierzo (Aragon north wind), even though its name -that could be translated as &#34;Far away Relative&#34;-is related to genetic biology. The place where the monument has been put &#8211;next to the Yacht Club- was attributed first to a work of art planned by Luc&#237;a Onza&#237;n: a galaxy of bright and floating signs on the Ebro, that was not carried out finally. </p><p>Walking down the left bank of the river and after passing the Archbishop Palace, we will find a picturesque house from the 1980s with odd pillars. If we stare at it, we will check that those pillars do not support that structure. This postmodern dwelling holds the Museum of the Roman River Port. The goal of the glass openings built on the low part is to make visible part of its contents to the citizens who are walking outside. It is worthwhile to have a look at San Bruno Square, where we find a very characteristic sculpture from the important Malaga artist Miguel Berrocal, named <a shape="rect" href="/sede/servicio/arte-publico/56">Torso Vectra</a>, a donation made by Opel Espa&#241;a to the city of Zaragoza in 1996 to celebrate the success of the car model Vectra, that had just been modified after its launching in 1998.   </p>
</sede:content></body></html>