<!DOCTYPE html><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:th="http://www.thymeleaf.org" xmlns:sede="http://www.zaragoza.es" lang="es"><head><meta charset="utf-8" />    <sede:meta title="Arte Publico. Itinerario Plazas del Casco Viejo. Plaza del Pilar" description="Itinerario Plazas del Casco Viejo. Plaza del Pilar" author="" last-modified="Fri Jan 16 00:00:00 GMT+01:00 2009" keywords="Arte Publico, itinerario."/></head><body><sede:content>
<h2>7. First Extension (Optional Route)</h2><ul id="menu_interior" class="nav nav-pills"><li><a href="/sede/portal/arte-publico/itinerarios/">Route Start</a></li><li><a href="este">Previous</a></li></ul>

<p>To complete our visit to Torrero Cemetery, we can take a look at the so-called First Extension, planned in the 30s and redesigned on the next decade by several architects. We will enter by the gate next to the main one, going out of the Old Cemetery on the right. This rectangular-shape area is structured around a main axe -the Fallen Path on an east-west orientation. There are no masterpieces here, and is composed of brickwork tombstones and chapels.</p><div class="dere pull-right margin-l05em"><img src="/cont/paginas/artepublico/itinerarios/img/cementerio/Foto15.JPG" alt=""/></div><p>First, we arrive at la Paz Square, a wide area with cypresses and pines where we can see a small obelisk made in granite, in honour of Jos&#233; de Yarza and Joaqu&#237;n Octavio de Toledo, civil servants of the City of Zaragoza dead in a terrorist attack in 1920. Going to the east by the Fallen Path, we turn right into the Third Street. Here we find the <a shape="rect" href="https://www.zaragoza.es/ciudad/cementerio/enlace/artepublico/itinerarios/cementerio/detalle_ArtePublico?id=97">&#34;Monument to those who died for Freedom and Democracy, 1936-1939 and  Postwar&#34;</a>, a simple monolith built in artificial stone. It was erected in 1980 in honour of those Republicans who died during the Civil War and the postwar, and also against Franco&#180;s rule. Going along to the end of the path, we arrive at a building similar to a rural chapel surrounded by tombstones with ceramic closings -the &#34;Monument to Franco Soldiers Fallen in Aragon Front&#34;. Behind it, we can see the Evangelical, Civil and Muslim cemeteries.</p><p>We come back by the Path of the Fallen till the access gate.</p>
</sede:content></body></html>