<!DOCTYPE html><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:th="http://www.thymeleaf.org" xmlns:sede="http://www.zaragoza.es" lang="es"><head><meta charset="utf-8" />    <sede:meta title="Arte Publico. Itinerario Plazas del Casco Viejo. Plaza del Pilar" description="Itinerario Plazas del Casco Viejo. Plaza del Pilar" author="" last-modified="Fri Jan 16 00:00:00 GMT+01:00 2009" keywords="Arte Publico, itinerario."/></head><body><sede:content>
<h2>3. Contemporary Cemetery (Optional Route)</h2><ul id="menu_interior" class="nav nav-pills"><li><a href="/sede/portal/arte-publico/itinerarios/">Route Start</a></li><li><a href="costa">Previous</a></li><li><a href="d">Next</a></li></ul>

<p>Here, we include the two last works made in the cemetery. From Costa Extension we can go downstairs to the Third and Fourth Extensions. But, before that, we go westbound to the right, passing the new chapels planned by Francisco Al&#243;s in the 70s. Crossing to the opposite side and a little bit to the west, we see the <a href="/sede/servicio/arte-publico/207" shape="rect">Monument to the Homeland</a> -originally named Monument to the Heroes and Martyrs of Our Glorious Crusade- (planned in 1943). This monument is placed opposite to the big rotunda for entering into the last extensions of the cemetery. It is an architectural and monumental construction placed at the Pilar Square in 1953. It was moved to the cemetery, acquiring a new meaning. </p><div class="dere pull-right margin-l05em"><img src="/cont/paginas/artepublico/itinerarios/img/cementerio/Foto7.JPG" alt=""/></div><p>We will take now the route to the Funerary Complex, place where the morgue and the chapels are situated. We can see there functional buildings made in brick, concrete and glass. This is the area with the biggest activity, and with a constant flux of people and cars. </p><p>After passing the last building of the Complex, we turn south -to the right according to the direction of our walk- and we will look for &#34;H&#34; street. We go straight and cross the first three blocks of tombs. Here starts a sloped trail that takes us to a hill with a covered trail that drives us to the collective pantheon of distinguished figures and the surrounding area named viewpoint-cloister. The whole group -that forms part of the Fourth Extension, planned between 1985 and 1990- has been made by the municipal architect Elvira Adiego. She explains that her goal was &#34;to establish a dialogue with the elements of the landscape, sky, mounts with pines, the morgue and Costa Viewpoint&#34;. Her best decision was to carry out an adequate integration of the elements with Zaragoza&#180;s tough landscape. An interesting detail is the fact that brick -one of the main materials of the cemetery- has not been used here. From this point, we can walk back from the same route or go on northbound along the Viewpoint Street, going back again to the Ancient Cemetery through the upstairs that give access to Costa Extension.  </p><div class="dere pull-right margin-l05em"><img src="/cont/paginas/artepublico/itinerarios/img/cementerio/Foto8.JPG" alt=""/></div>
</sede:content></body></html>