<!DOCTYPE html><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:th="http://www.thymeleaf.org" xmlns:sede="http://www.zaragoza.es" lang="es"><head><meta charset="utf-8" />    <sede:meta title="Arte Publico. Itinerario Plazas del Casco Viejo. Plaza del Pilar" description="Itinerario Plazas del Casco Viejo. Plaza del Pilar" author="" last-modified="Fri Jan 16 00:00:00 GMT+01:00 2009" keywords="Arte Publico, itinerario."/></head><body><sede:content>
<h2>6. Path A (East Side)</h2><ul id="menu_interior" class="nav nav-pills"><li><a href="/sede/portal/arte-publico/itinerarios/">Route Start</a></li><li><a href="comun">Previous</a></li><li><a href="ampliacion">Nex</a></li></ul>

<div class="dere pull-right margin-l05em"><img alt="" src="/cont/paginas/artepublico/itinerarios/img/cementerio/Foto13.JPG"/></div><p>Already in path  &#34;A&#34;, we turn left to the west and go to the main access gate of the cemetery. On the right, there are blocks of tombs and other chapels which follow also Magdalena plans. On the left, we can see family vaults with different styles and quality.</p><p>Going along, we will stop at the Herrero Family Vault (1920), the most genuine example inspired by the old Egyptian culture: columns and lotus-shaped capitals, a big sphinx, tall obelisks, and a cross with lotus-shape arms.  Beyond, the striking family vault of the family Repulles de la Llata (1941) shows the moment when an angel going downstairs gets closer a sarcophagus announcing the Final Judgement. There are also sphinxes and candelabra. The family vault of the Horno&#180;s, is also an eclectic and historicist work, formed by a small rationalist template designed by the architect Fernando Garc&#237;a Mercadal, without any ornament. </p><div class="dere pull-right margin-l05em"><img alt="" src="/cont/paginas/artepublico/itinerarios/img/cementerio/Foto14.JPG"/></div><p>A little bit beyond, the family vault of the family Albert, Ballar&#237;n, Izquierdo and Perez (1882), is formed by a complex Latin cross with attached columns and plentiful of funerary symbology on its base, such as owls or heads of angels with open wings. And, finally, the Condes de Fuentes&#180; Vault (1900), is a simple, smart and Neoclassic work of art for containing two coffins. Made in high-quality white marble, we can highlight one of its fronts with a big coat of arms of the family. The group si surrounded by an artistic fence made in wrought iron.</p><p>Here ends the route by the Ancient Cemetery. We are once again at the access gate, our starting point. </p>
</sede:content></body></html>