<!DOCTYPE html><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:th="http://www.thymeleaf.org" xmlns:sede="http://www.zaragoza.es" lang="es"><head><meta charset="utf-8" />    <sede:meta title="Arte Publico. Itinerario Plazas del Casco Viejo. Plaza de la Seo" description="Itinerario Plazas del Casco Viejo. Plaza de la Seo" author="" last-modified="Mon Sep 28 00:00:00 GMT+01:00 2009" keywords="Arte Publico, itinerario."/></head><body><sede:content>
<h2>2. La Seo Square</h2><ul id="menu_interior" class="nav nav-pills"><li><a href="/sede/portal/arte-publico/itinerarios/">Route Start</a></li><li><a href="pilar">Previous</a></li><li><a href="sanbruno">Next</a></li></ul><p>In 1988, Julio D&#237;az-Palacios drew up a remodelation project to return its singular character to this square, highlighting its isolation from the different heights between the square and Don Jaime Street, and giving it a warmer and peaceful aspect. While taking samples &#8211;compulsory before starting a work in the old town- archaeological structures of public use and singular importance appeared. This discovery forced to change the initial project for another one made by Jos&#233; Manuel P&#233;rez Latorre in June 1989. </p><div class="dere pull-right margin-l05em"><img src="//www.zaragoza.es/cont/paginas/artepublico/itinerarios/img/3.jpg" alt="" class="img-responsive" /></div><p>The goal of the new plan was basically to preserve the archaeological remains, and give this place back the old dignity required by the presence of the cathedral. According to P&#233;rez Latorre, the conservation of the remains should be done in a way that could allow citizens to contemplate it. A subterranean hall with 2,000 m2 was planned, supported by an over-size structure made of white concrete which contrasted with the general brownish-grey tone of the Roman remains. In order to make possible a direct vision of the remains, several linked footbridges were planned, giving access to a big exhibition hall placed in a lower level. </p><p>The plan was to leave proof on its surface of the "modernity" of the square, which formed part of a bigger group, and, at the same time was composed of autonomous buildings. Fountains, which serve also as benches, produce a certain comfort, suppressing small-scale elements as well as the traffic barrier of Don Jaime Street. Travertine marble which reflects light on buildings was used for the pavement. </p><p>It was also planned a building which did not create visual interferences with the <a shape="rect" href="/sede/servicio/arte-publico/298">facade of the Cathedral</a> and the Archbishop Palace, allowing visitors to have access to the subterranean archaeological remains. According to P&#233;rez Latorre, it is an onyx structure with a texture made only by reflected light. The idea of the shape came from the Baroque Tower of La Seo, with the integration also of the Berninian baldaquin, that is, a dose and four supporting elements. The goal of this structure was to preserve the heritage from our origins, harmonizing it, with the biggest dignity, with the architecture of the square. </p>
</sede:content></body></html>