<!DOCTYPE html><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:th="http://www.thymeleaf.org" xmlns:sede="http://www.zaragoza.es" lang="es"><head><meta charset="utf-8" />    <sede:meta title="Arte Publico. Itinerario Plazas del Casco Viejo. Plaza de San Pedro Nolasco" description="Itinerario Plazas del Casco Viejo. Plaza de San Pedro Nolasco" author="" last-modified="Fri Jan 16 00:00:00 GMT+01:00 2009" keywords="Arte Publico, itinerario."/></head><body><sede:content>
<h2>4. San Pedro Nolasco Square</h2><ul id="menu_interior" class="nav nav-pills"><li><a href="/sede/portal/arte-publico/itinerarios/">Route Start</a></li><li><a href="sanbruno">Previous</a></li><li><a href="sinues">Next</a></li></ul><div class="dere pull-right margin-l05em"><img alt="" src="/cont/paginas/artepublico/itinerarios/img/nolasco.jpg"/></div><p>Now, we go out of San Vicente de Paul Street and turn into San Jorge Street, arriving easily to San Pedro Nolasco Square. This square was remodelled in April 1990 by a team headed by Ricardo Us&#243;n Garc&#237;a, who pedestrianized the majority of the area. San Jorge is the only street where road traffic is allowed, including also the junction in angle between this street and San Lorenzo. The Monument to the Argensola&#180;s was also moved, releasing the central area and enlarging the green zone. A concentric model is established, from the position of the trees at the center  -the true protagonists of the square- to a second rectangular-arranged group of trees, for putting order to the peripheral elements: lamp posts, the monument-fountain and the bar-kiosk. <a shape="rect" href="/sede/servicio/arte-publico/94">The Monument to the Argensola&#180;s</a>, made by Jos&#233; Bueno in 1923, is a unidirectional work, therefore its place at the center of the square was not convenient. It was placed at a side, highlighted by a visual vertical support. The kiosk had an adequate size and site, but the composition did not match the surrounding area. Therefore, a group composed of two small volumes -made in white concrete, rounded off with white artificial stone and covered with marble sheet- was planned.  Light was provided by four towers placed at the diagonals of the area, and, for the pavement, spike-shape Calatorao black stone was used in Argensola Street. The benches were made in artificial prefabricated white stone.  </p>
</sede:content></body></html>