<!DOCTYPE html><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:th="http://www.thymeleaf.org" xmlns:sede="http://www.zaragoza.es" lang="es"><head><meta charset="utf-8" />    <sede:meta title="Arte Publico. Itinerario Plazas del Casco Viejo. Plaza de Jose Sinues" description="Itinerario Plazas del Casco Viejo. Plaza de josé Sinues" author="" last-modified="Fri Jan 16 00:00:00 GMT+01:00 2009" keywords="Arte Publico, itinerario."/></head><body><sede:content>
<h2>5. José Sinués Square</h2><ul id="menu_interior" class="nav nav-pills"><li><a href="/sede/portal/arte-publico/itinerarios/">Route Start</a></li><li><a href="nolasco">Previous</a></li><li><a href="arino">Next</a></li></ul><div class="dere pull-right margin-l05em"><img alt="" src="/cont/paginas/artepublico/itinerarios/img/sinues.jpg"/></div><p>Going along San Jorge Street, we arrive at Don Jaime Street. Then, we turn left, and some metres ahead, we find Jos&#233; Sinu&#233;s Square. The remodelling of this square, with the restoration of the Principal Theatre, was planned in 1984. In both cases, the plan was made by Jos&#233; Manuel P&#233;rez Latorre, and considers the square as a place for resting, built with monochrome and noble materials such as stone, creating a visual support area for the theatre. The square had a totally irregular shape and was conditioned by the fact that the <a shape="rect" href="/sede/servicio/arte-publico/213">sculpture made by Pablo Serrano and devoted to Jos&#233; Sinu&#233;s</a>, must remain there. Giving the biggest visibility to the facade of the Principal Theatre, determined the site of this sculpture and of the rest of the new urban furniture. Parallel to Don Jaime and isolating the square, it was planned to place the above mentioned sculpture and a monumental fountain made of grey granite. Other elements that define the square are the street lamps placed at the lowest part of the Theatre&#180;s facade, inserted as sculptural elements. The idea of using a foreshortened positioning was to form a visual vault for closing the opposite facade to the Theatre. A minimalist design was used for the benches - a surface and a support made of teak with stainless steel feet.</p><p>Finally, the trees -Robinea Pseudoacacia- are the same as those planted at Veronica Street. </p><div class="dere pull-right margin-l05em"><img src="/cont/paginas/artepublico/itinerarios/img/sinues2.jpg" alt=""/></div>
</sede:content></body></html>