<!DOCTYPE html><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:th="http://www.thymeleaf.org" xmlns:sede="http://www.zaragoza.es" lang="es"><head><meta charset="utf-8" />    <sede:meta title="Arte Publico. Itinerario Plazas del Casco Viejo. Plaza de Ariño" description="Itinerario Plazas del Casco Viejo. Plaza de Ariño" author="" last-modified="Fri Jan 16 00:00:00 GMT+01:00 2009" keywords="Arte Publico, itinerario."/></head><body><sede:content>
<h2>6. Ariño Square</h2><ul id="menu_interior" class="nav nav-pills"><li><a href="/sede/portal/arte-publico/itinerarios/">Route Start</a></li><li><a href="sinues">Previous</a></li><li><a href="felipe">Next</a></li></ul><div class="dere pull-right margin-l05em"><img alt="" src="/cont/paginas/artepublico/itinerarios/img/arino.jpg"/></div><p>We walk back and go along Don Jaime Street, turning at <a shape="rect" href="/sede/servicio/arte-publico/284">the facade of the CAI</a> (saving bank) at Ari&#241;o Square, where we can see <a shape="rect" href="/sede/servicio/arte-publico/186">the monument to the filmmaker Eduardo Gimeno</a>. This square was built near the Ari&#241;o&#180;s Palace and placed on a surface made of random materials. Due to this,  creaks appeared on the pavement and the stairs going from Don Jaime to the square. In order to solve those problems, a restricted contest of ideas was called. The winner was the team formed by &#193;ngel Hern&#225;ndez Parejo, Pilar L&#243;pez Ruiz and Isabela de Renter&#237;a Cano, who, in February 1990, drew back the project for remodelling Ari&#241;o Square, and San F&#233;lix and San Voto streets. This horizontal-shape square forms a slope of one metre at floor level, between this street and Don Jaime. The difference of level is overcome on both ends by ramps and stairs. A fountain was placed at the center to join both areas through a sloped plane made of Calatorao polished stone. Three lights, serving as banner, were placed at one of the sides, and the rest of benches on the other. On the opposite side, we can see two lines of trees and the rest of benches. </p>
</sede:content></body></html>