<!DOCTYPE html><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:th="http://www.thymeleaf.org" xmlns:sede="http://www.zaragoza.es" lang="es"><head><meta charset="utf-8" />    <sede:meta title="Arte Publico. Itinerario Plazas del Casco Viejo. Plaza del Pilar" description="Itinerario Plazas del Casco Viejo. Plaza del Pilar" author="" last-modified="Fri Jan 16 00:00:00 GMT+01:00 2009" keywords="Arte Publico, itinerario."/></head><body><sede:content>
<h2>7. San Felipe Square</h2><ul id="menu_interior" class="nav nav-pills"><li><a href="/sede/portal/arte-publico/itinerarios/">Route Start</a></li><li><a href="arino">Previous</a></li><li><a href="justicia">Next</a></li></ul><div class="dere pull-right margin-l05em"><img src="/cont/paginas/artepublico/itinerarios/img/felipe2.jpg" alt=""/></div><p>Going along San F&#233;lix Street we arrive at M&#233;ndez N&#250;&#241;ez Street, and then, towards the west side and crossing Alfonso I Street, we enter into Torre Nueva Street. Some metres beyond, we are in front of San Felipe Square.  This square is one of the most traditional areas of the old town. At the beginning of the 16th century, there was built the so-called Torre Nueva (New Tower) -demolished in 1892- surrounded by representative buildings such as <a shape="rect" href="/sede/servicio/arte-publico/283">San Felipe Church</a>  and its Baroque facade, Pablo Gargallo Museum, the House of the Marquis of Villaverde or Argillo House (with equestrian sculptures representing the <a shape="rect" href="/sede/servicio/arte-publico/list?titleContains=saludo">classic and the modern athlete</a>, Fortea, Montal and Fuenclara houses, etc. The different heights of the square&#180;s pavement overpass sometimes the thresholds of the buildings around it. On the other hand and in spite of its demolition the Torre Nueva continued to be present. Recently, its remains dugging boosted the idea of a certain physical presence. Finally, problems such as traffic must be solved, therefore road traffic is restricted in the area. </p><p>In order to solve these problems, the architects Fernando Aguerri, Miguel &#193;ngel Bordej&#233;, Carlos Bressel, Javier Ibarg&#252;en and Javier Pe&#241;a, with the initial collaboration of Roberto Benedicto and Joaqu&#237;n Soro, drew up in December 1989 the project for the remodelation of San Felipe Square and the nearby streets. In the project, Gil Berges Street became a pedestrianized area, but nevertheless cars could circulate occasionally. Therefore, a continuous pavement made of Calatorao stone was planned in order to allow pedestrians to pass. At the confluence with Alfonso Street, on a corner, it was placed a small stone fountain as well as a new stone fountain with four spouts.</p><div class="dere pull-right margin-l05em"><img src="/cont/paginas/artepublico/itinerarios/img/felipe1.jpg" alt=""/></div><p>At the square, the floor level was lowered to the previous height. Over the remains of the Torre Nueva, <a shape="rect" href="/sede/servicio/arte-publico/153">the Memorial to the Torre Nueva</a> was built, an ephemeral construction that symbolized the presence of the tower. The symbolism was reflected on its shape: a star-shape floor formed by macael marble panels. Access was through the place occupied by the old gate, being closed by a light rail with lights on the supporting posts. Trees and macael marble benches (made in Calatorao stone with backs made of sheets of wood) continued to be present on the rest of the square. It was also placed a small bronze figure not included in the initial plan and representing a boy sitting on the floor and looking up to the demolished tower. This memorial sculpture did not satisfy citizens that pretended -and still pretend- the reconstruction of the Torre Nueva, and,  those who considered that its size was out of proportion, were also bothered. The monument became a rubbish dump until its demolition in March 2002. Presently, only the octagonal-shape ground floor remembers its presence. </p>
</sede:content></body></html>