<!DOCTYPE html>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:th="http://www.thymeleaf.org" xmlns:sede="http://www.zaragoza.es" lang="en">

<head>
    <meta charset="utf-8" />
    <sede:meta title="Clarity Project" description="The CLARITY project is a two-year project funded by the European Commission under the Horizon 2020 framework, that brings together stakeholder networks across Europe into an engaged and mobilised community that supports innovation in open eGovernment applications." author="Ayuntamiento de Zaragoza" keywords="Clarity project, European Commission, Horizon 2020, Europe, eGovernment, transparency">
    </sede:meta>
   <link rel="stylesheet" href="//www.zaragoza.es/cont/vistas/portal/clarity/css/blueprint.css" />
</head>

<body>
    <sede:content>
        <img class="cabecera img-responsive full-width" src="/cont/paginas/clarity/img/clarity-cover-2.jpg" alt="" />   

        <div class="card clearfix">
            <h2>Introduction</h2>
            <hr class="sm" />
<p>There is an existing demand on governments to provide an environment that ensures openness and efficiency in the delivery of services. ICTs can help here, but this requires an optimization of the role ICTs play. How should ICTs be integrated into governance and include citizen engagement and participation to enhance accountability, transparency and trust? There are not only technical issues, but also social, organisational and cultural ones.</p>
<p>This deliverable report D4.1: Blueprint for next steps in eGovernment applications in Europe, presents an initial blueprint of the next steps required for the provision and uptake of eGovernment applications and services in each of the following four public sector areas: (a) general practice health, (b) local government, (c) small business and self-employed and (d) disability in the EU. Focusing on particular sectors does not mean that the proposed recommendations do not follow a holistic approach to open eGovernment, they just highlight some particularities regarding each sector.</p>
<p>This deliverable draws on previous deliverables from WP2 and WP3<small><a href="#footnote">1</a></small> and integrates and complements their findings on:
<ol>
<li>available and emerging solutions</li><li>
emerging business models</li><li>
technology and data gaps</li><li>
emerging data models</li><li>
policy gaps</li><li>
social considerations</li>
</ol></p>
<p>This initial blueprint will be exposed for feedback: i) at a validation workshop with multiple stakeholders involved in encouraging the adoption of eGovernment applications in Europe, and ii) via a range of assessment activities reaching out to the project contact list and wider network. Feedback from these evaluative activities will be presented and integrated to enhance the final blueprint to be presented in deliverable D4.2.</p>
<p>The report is structured as follows: 
<ul>
<li>Section 2 summarises the general recommendations for the provision and adoption of open eGovernment services in Europe.</li>
<li>Sections 3 to 6 provide details for each of the aforementioned sectors, so that people interested in just one section do not need to read the other three sections to get a complete picture. Each section has information on:
<ul>
<li>Open eGovernment in the corresponding sector</li>
<li>Main available and emerging solutions</li>
<li>Main available and emerging business and data models</li>
<li>Main gaps in policy, technology and data</li>
<li>Social considerations</li>
<li>Recommendations based on the previous subsections</li></ul></li>
<li>Section 7 explains the validation plans.</li></ul>
</p>
<div id="footnote">
<small>1 All CLARITY deliverables are available on the project website at: http://clarity-csa.eu/resources</small></div>
</div>
				
		
    </sede:content>
    
</body>

</html>
